All right. So, like all good stories,
حسناً. إذاً كما في جميع القصص الجميلة
this starts a long, long time ago
تبدأ هذه منذ زمن بعيد جداً
when there was basically nothing.
حينما لم يكن هناك أي شيء
So here is a complete picture of the universe
إذاً هنا صورة كاملة للكون
about 14-odd billion years ago.
قبل قرابة 14 مليار سنة
All energy is concentrated into a single point of energy.
كل الطاقة متركزة في نقطة طاقة واحدة
For some reason it explodes,
ولسبب ما انفجرت
and you begin to get these things.
وبدأت تتلقى هذه الأشياء
So you're now about 14 billion years into this.
والآن نحن بعد 14 مليار سنة من هذا.
And these things expand and expand and expand
وهذه الاشياء تتوسع أكثر فأكثر فأكثر
into these giant galaxies,
لتكون هذه المجرات العملاقة،
and you get trillions of them.
فتنشأ ترليونات منها.
And within these galaxies
وبداخل هذه المجرات
you get these enormous dust clouds.
تتكون سحب الغبار الكبيرة هذه.
And I want you to pay particular attention
وأريدكم أن تبدوا اهتماما خاصا
to the three little prongs
بهذه الشوكات الثلاث الصغيرة
in the center of this picture.
في منتصف هذه الصورة.
If you take a close-up of those,
اذا أخذت لقطة مقربة لها،
they look like this.
ستبدو هكذا.
And what you're looking at is columns of dust
والذي ترونه هنا هو أعمدة من الغبار
where there's so much dust --
حيث هناك الكثير من الأغبرة --
by the way, the scale of this is a trillion vertical miles --
وبالمناسبة، بعد هذا هو ترليون ميل عمودي --
and what's happening is there's so much dust,
والحاصل الآن هو أن هناك الكثير من الغبار،
it comes together and it fuses
يتجمع ليندمج
and ignites a thermonuclear reaction.
ويطلق تفاعلا نوويا حراريا
And so what you're watching
والذي ترونه الآن
is the birth of stars.
هو ولادة النجوم.
These are stars being born out of here.
هذه نجوم تولد من هنا.
When enough stars come out,
وحين تظهر نجوم كافية،
they create a galaxy.
فهي تكون مجرة.
This one happens to be a particularly important galaxy,
وهذه بالذات هي مجرة مهمة،
because you are here.
لأنكم هنا الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And as you take a close-up of this galaxy,
وحينما تأخذون صورة مقربة لهذه المجرة،
you find a relatively normal,
ستجدون نجمة عادية نوعاً ما،
not particularly interesting star.
ولا تملك أي شيء مميز.
By the way, you're now about two-thirds of the way into this story.
بالمناسبة، أنتم الآن في ثلثي القصة.
So this star doesn't even appear
هذه النجمة لا تظهر حتى
until about two-thirds of the way into this story.
إلا بعد ثلثي القصة.
And then what happens
وما يحدث بعد ذلك
is there's enough dust left over
أن هناك بقايا غبار كافية
that it doesn't ignite into a star,
لا تنصهر لتكون نجمة،
it becomes a planet.
ولكن تكون كوكبا.
And this is about a little over four billion years ago.
وكان هذا قبل أكثر من قرابة أربعة ملايير سنة
And soon thereafter
وبعد ذلك بفترة
there's enough material left over
هناك بقايا مواد كافية
that you get a primordial soup,
للحصول على حساء بدائي،
and that creates life.
وهذا يخلق الحياة.
And life starts to expand and expand and expand,
وتبدأ الحياة بالتوسع أكثر فأكثر فأكثر
until it goes kaput.
حتى تفلس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now the really strange thing
والآن الشيء الغريب فعلا
is life goes kaput, not once, not twice,
هو أن الحياة تقلس ليس لمرة واحدة أو مرتين
but five times.
ولكن لخمس مرات.
So almost all life on Earth
وبالتالي فجل الحياة على الأرض
is wiped out about five times.
محيت قرابة الخمس مرات.
And as you're thinking about that,
ومن خلال تفكيركم بهذا،
what happens is you get more and more complexity,
تحصلون على تعقيد أكثر وأكثر،
more and more stuff
مواد أكثر فأكثر
to build new things with.
لبناء أشياء أحدث.
And we don't appear
ولا نظهر نحن
until about 99.96 percent of the time into this story,
الا بعد 99.96 في المئة من وقت بداية هذه القصة،
just to put ourselves and our ancestors in perspective.
فقظ لنضع أنفسنا ومن سبقونا داخل المنظور.
So within that context, there's two theories of the case
إذن، وفي هذا الإطار، توجد نظريتان لهذا الحالة
as to why we're all here.
لتفسر لما نحن جميعا هنا.
The first theory of the case
النظرية الأولى لهذه الحالة
is that's all she wrote.
أن هذا هو كل ما حدث.
Under that theory,
و تحت هذه النظرية،
we are the be-all and end-all
نكون نحن الفاعل الكلي و النهاية الكلية.
of all creation.
لكل الخليقة.
And the reason for trillions of galaxies,
والهدف من تريليونات المجرات،
sextillions of planets,
وسكستليونات الكواكب،
is to create something that looks like that
هو خلق شئ يبدو مثل هذا
and something that looks like that.
و شئ يبدو مثل هذا.
And that's the purpose of the universe;
وهذا هو الغرض من الكون؛
and then it flat-lines,
ومن ثم يكون خط مستو،
it doesn't get any better.
و الوضع لا يصبح أفضل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The only question you might want to ask yourself is,
السؤال الوحيد الذي قد تطرحه على نفسك،
could that be just mildly arrogant?
هل من الممكن أن تكون هذه الفكرة مغرورة بعض الشئ؟
And if it is --
وإن كانت كذلك --
and particularly given the fact that we came very close to extinction.
وتحديدا بعد حقيقة أننا اقتربنا جدا من الإنقراض.
There were only about 2,000 of our species left.
كان هناك حوالي 2,000 فرد فقط من صنفنا.
A few more weeks without rain,
بضعة أسابيع أخرى من دون مطر،
we would have never seen any of these.
ما كنا سنرى أيا من هذا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So maybe you have to think about a second theory
إذن، ربما يجب أن نفكر في نظرية أخرى
if the first one isn't good enough.
إذا كانت الأولى ليست جيدة بما يكفي.
Second theory is: Could we upgrade?
النظرية الثانية هي: هل من الممكن أن نترقى؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, why would one ask a question like that?
حسنا، لماذا يسأل شخص ما مثل هذا السؤال؟
Because there have been at least 29 upgrades so far
لأنه كانت هناك 29 ترقية على الأقل حتى الآن
of humanoids.
للإنسانيين.
So it turns out that we have upgraded.
إذن، يتضح لنا أننا قد ترقينا من قبل.
We've upgraded time and again and again.
لقد ترقينا مرة ومرة أخرى ومرة أخرى.
And it turns out that we keep discovering upgrades.
واتضح أننا لازلنا نكتشف ترقيات جديدة.
We found this one last year.
لقد اكتشفنا هذه العام الماضي.
We found another one last month.
واكتشفنا واحدة أخرى الشهر الماضي.
And as you're thinking about this,
وحين تفكرون في هذا
you might also ask the question:
يمكنكم أيضا أن تطرحوا سؤالا
So why a single human species?
لماذا صنف واحد فقط من البشر؟
Wouldn't it be really odd
أليس هذا غريبا
if you went to Africa and Asia and Antarctica
إذا ذهبت إلى افريقيا و آسيا و القارة القطبية الجنوبية
and found exactly the same bird --
ووجدت نفس الصنف من طائر ما
particularly given that we co-existed at the same time
خاصة إذا علمت أننا تواجدنا في نفس الوقت
with at least eight other versions of humanoid
مع ما لا يقل عن ثمانية نسخ من الإنسانيين
at the same time on this planet?
في نفس الوقت على هذا الكوكب.
So the normal state of affairs
إذن فالوضع الطبيعي
is not to have just a Homo sapiens;
ليس هو وجود فقط الـ "هومو سابيين"؛
the normal state of affairs
الوضع الطبيعي
is to have various versions of humans walking around.
هو أن يكون هناك أنواع مختلفة من البشر يتحركون من حولنا.
And if that is the normal state of affairs,
وإذا كان هذا هو الوضع الطبيعي،
then you might ask yourself,
فمن الممكن أن تسألوا أنفسكم سؤالا
all right, so if we want to create something else,
حسنا، إذا أردنا التطور لشئ آخر
how big does a mutation have to be?
أي درجة يجب أن تكون عليه الطفرات؟
Well Svante Paabo has the answer.
حسنا، سفانتي بابو يملك الإجابة.
The difference between humans and Neanderthal
الفرق بين الإنسان والإنسان البدائي
is 0.004 percent of gene code.
هو 0,004 بالمائة من الترميز الوراثي.
That's how big the difference is
هذه هو حجم الفرق
one species to another.
بين صنف وآخر.
This explains most contemporary political debates.
هذا يفسر أغلب الجدالات السياسية المعاصرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But as you're thinking about this,
ولكن وأنتم تفكرون في هذا
one of the interesting things
واحدة من الأشياء المثيرة للاهتمام
is how small these mutations are and where they take place.
هو مدى دقة هذه التحولات والأماكن التي يحدث بها التحول.
Difference human/Neanderthal
الفرق بين الإنسان والإنسان البدائي
is sperm and testis,
هو الحيوان المنوي والخصية،
smell and skin.
حاسة الشم والجلد.
And those are the specific genes
وهذه هي المورثات المعينة لذلك
that differ from one to the other.
والتي تختلف من واحد إلى الآخر.
So very small changes can have a big impact.
إذن تحولات صغيرة جدا قد تمثل تأثيرا كبير.
And as you're thinking about this,
وفي حين تفكرون في ذلك،
we're continuing to mutate.
نحن نستمر في التحور.
So about 10,000 years ago by the Black Sea,
فمنذ حوالي 10.000 سنة بجوار البحر الأسود،
we had one mutation in one gene
حدث لنا تحول واحد في جين واحد
which led to blue eyes.
والذي أدى إلى العيون الزرقاء.
And this is continuing and continuing and continuing.
وهذا يستمر ويستمر ويستمر
And as it continues,
وبينما يستمر،
one of the things that's going to happen this year
واحدة من الأشياء التي ستحدث هذا العام
is we're going to discover the first 10,000 human genomes,
هو أننا سنكتشف أول 10.000 مورثة بشرية،
because it's gotten cheap enough to do the gene sequencing.
لأنه أصبح رخيصا بما فيه الكفاية أن تحصل على التسلسل الوراثي.
And when we find these,
وحين نحصل على هذه،
we may find differences.
من الممكن أن نجد الفروق.
And by the way, this is not a debate that we're ready for,
وبالمناسبة، هذا ليس جدالا نحن مستعدون له،
because we have really misused the science in this.
لأننا أسأنا استخدام العلم في هذا المجال
In the 1920s, we thought there were major differences between people.
في عشرينيات القرن العشرين، ظننا أن هناك فروق كبيرة بين البشر.
That was partly based on Francis Galton's work.
وهذا كان يستند بصورة جزئية على أعمال فرانسيس جالتون
He was Darwin's cousin.
كان ابن عم داروين.
But the U.S., the Carnegie Institute,
ولكن الولايات المتحدة، معهد كارنيجي،
Stanford, American Neurological Association
جامعة ستانفورد، الجمعية العصبية الأمريكية
took this really far.
ذهبوا بها إلى حد بعيد حقا.
That got exported and was really misused.
والذي تم تصديره وأسيئ استخدامه بشدة.
In fact, it led to some absolutely horrendous
في الواقع، لقد قاد إلى التعامل بطريقة رهيبة
treatment of human beings.
مع بعض البشر.
So since the 1940s, we've been saying there are no differences,
فمنذ الأربعينيات، ونحن نقول أنه لا توجد فروق
we're all identical.
نحن جميعا متطابقون.
We're going to know at year end if that is true.
ونحن سنكتشف بنهاية العام مدى صدق هذا.
And as we think about that,
وفي حين نفكر في هذا،
we're actually beginning to find things
نحن في الحقيقة بدأنا في اكتشاف أشياء
like, do you have an ACE gene?
مثل، هل تملك مورثة ACE؟
Why would that matter?
لماذا قد يكون هذا مهما؟
Because nobody's ever climbed an 8,000-meter peak without oxygen
لأنه ما من أحد تسلق قمة جبل طولها 8,000 متر من دون أوكسجين
that doesn't have an ACE gene.
وذلك بدون أن يمتلك مورثة ACE
And if you want to get more specific,
وإذا أردنا أن نصبح أكثر تحديدا
how about a 577R genotype?
ماذا عن النمط الوراثي 577R
Well it turns out that every male Olympic power athelete ever tested
حسنا، لقد اتضح أنه كل لاعب قوى أوليمبي ذكر تم اختباره
carries at least one of these variants.
يحمل على الأقل أحد أنواعه
If that is true,
لو كان هذا صحيحا،
it leads to some very complicated questions
فإنه يؤدي إلى بعض الأسئلة المعقدة جدا
for the London Olympics.
لأوليمبياد لندن.
Three options:
ثلاثة خيارات:
Do you want the Olympics to be a showcase
هل تريدون أن تكون الأوليمبياد عبارة عن استعراض
for really hardworking mutants?
لمجموعة من المتحولين وراثيا الذين يبذلون مجهودا شاقا جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Option number two:
الخيار الثاني:
Why don't we play it like golf or sailing?
لماذا لا نلعبها مثل الغولف أو الإبحار؟
Because you have one and you don't have one,
لأنك تحمل هذا النمط الوراثي وأنت لا تحمله،
I'll give you a tenth of a second head start.
فسأعطيك أفضلية البداية بعشر من الثانية.
Version number three:
الاختيار الثالث:
Because this is a naturally occurring gene
لأن هذه المورثة توجد في بعض الناس بشكل طبيعي
and you've got it and you didn't pick the right parents,
وأنت تحمله، وأنت لم تختر الوالدين الصحيحين
you get the right to upgrade.
فأنت تملك الحق كي تترقى
Three different options.
ثلاثة اختيارات مختلفة.
If these differences are the difference
لو كانت هذه الفروق هي الفرق
between an Olympic medal and a non-Olympic medal.
بين الميدالية الأوليمبية والميدالية الغير أوليمبية.
And it turns out that as we discover these things,
ويتبين لنا أنه في خلال اكتشافنا لهذه الأشياء،
we human beings really like to change
نحن البشر نحب حقا أن نتغيير
how we look, how we act,
كيف نبدو، كيف نتعامل،
what our bodies do.
ماذا تفعل أجسادنا.
And we had about 10.2 million plastic surgeries in the United States,
و قمنا بعمل حوالي 10.2 مليون عملية تجميل في الولايات المتحدة
except that with the technologies that are coming online today,
غير أنه بالتقنيات القادمة لنا عبر الإنترنت اليوم
today's corrections, deletions,
تصحيحات اليوم، والحذوفات
augmentations and enhancements
التكبير والتحسين
are going to seem like child's play.
سوف تبدو مثل لعب الأطفال.
You already saw the work by Tony Atala on TED,
لقد رأيتم بالفعل العمل الذي قام به توني عطالله على TED
but this ability to start filling
لكن هذه القدرة كي نبدأ بملء أشياء
things like inkjet cartridges with cells
مثل خرطوشة حبر الطابعة بالخلايا
are allowing us to print skin, organs
يسمح لنا بطباعة جلد، أعضاء
and a whole series of other body parts.
وسلسة كاملة من أجزاء الجسم الأخرى.
And as these technologies go forward,
وبينما تتقدم هذه التقنيات،
you keep seeing this, you keep seeing this, you keep seeing things --
تستمرفي رؤية هذا، تستمر في رؤية هذا ، تستمر في رؤية أشياء --
2000, human genome sequence --
تسلسل 2000 جينوم بشري --
and it seems like nothing's happening,
ويبدو أن شيئا لم يحدث،
until it does.
حتى يحدث.
And we may just be in some of these weeks.
و من الممكن أن نكون نحن في وسط هذه الأسابيع.
And as you're thinking about
وأنت تفكر في ذلك
these two guys sequencing a human genome in 2000
هذان الرجلين يفكان تسلسل الجينوم البشري في عام 2000
and the Public Project sequencing the human genome in 2000,
والمشروع العام لفك تسلسل الجينوم البشري في عام 2000
then you don't hear a lot,
ومن ثم لا تسمع الكثير،
until you hear about an experiment last year in China,
حتى تسمع عن تجربة العام الماضي بالصين
where they take skin cells from this mouse,
حيث أخذوا خلايا جلدية من هذا الفأر،
put four chemicals on it,
وضعوا أربعة مواد كيميائية عليها،
turn those skin cells into stem cells,
حولوا هذه الخلايا الجلدية إلى خلايا جذعية،
let the stem cells grow
تركوا الخلايا الجذعية تنمو
and create a full copy of that mouse.
وصنعوا نسخة كاملة من الفأر.
That's a big deal.
هذا شئ عظيم.
Because in essence
لأنه في الجوهر
what it means is you can take a cell,
ما يعنيه هو أنه يمكنك أن تأخذ خلية،
which is a pluripotent stem cell,
عبارة عن خلية جذعية محفزة،
which is like a skier at the top of a mountain,
ويمكن تشبيهها بمتزلج على قمة جبل،
and those two skiers become two pluripotent stem cells,
وهذين المتزلجين يصبحان خليتين جذعيتين محفزتين،
four, eight, 16,
أربعة، ثمانية، 16،
and then it gets so crowded
ومن ثم تصبح مزدحمة جدا
after 16 divisions
بعد 16 انقساما
that those cells have to differentiate.
لدرجة أن هذه الخلايا يجب أن تتمايز.
So they go down one side of the mountain,
فينزل بعضهم على ناحية واحدة من الجبل،
they go down another.
وينزل البعض على الناحية الأخرى.
And as they pick that,
وحين يختارون هذا الطريق،
these become bone,
تصبح الخلايا عظاما،
and then they pick another road and these become platelets,
وهذه تختار طريقا آخر وتصبح صفائح دموية
and these become macrophages,
وتصبح هذه خلايا ضامة،
and these become T cells.
وتصبح هذه خلايا T الدفاعية.
But it's really hard, once you ski down,
لكنه يكون من الصعب جدا حين تبدأ بالتزلج هبوطا،
to get back up.
أن تعود إلى الأعلى.
Unless, of course, if you have a ski lift.
إلا لو، بالطبع، كنت تملك رافعة متزلجين.
And what those four chemicals do
وما تفعله هذه المواد الكيميائية الأربعة
is they take any cell
أنها تأخذ أي خلية
and take it way back up the mountain
وتأخذها مرة أخرى إلى أعلى قمة الجبل
so it can become any body part.
وبالتالي يمكنها أن تتمايز إلى أي جزء من الجسم.
And as you think of that,
وحينما تفكر في ذلك
what it means is potentially
ما يعنيه هو أنه من المحتمل
you can rebuild a full copy
أن تتمكن من إعادة بناء نسخة كاملة
of any organism
من أي كائن
out of any one of its cells.
من أصل أي خلية من خلاياه
That turns out to be a big deal
الآن يتضح أن هذا أمر عظيم
because now you can take, not just mouse cells,
لأنه الآن لا يمكنك فقط أن تأخذ خلايا فأر،
but you can human skin cells
بل يمكنك أن تأخذ خلايا جلد إنسان
and turn them into human stem cells.
وتحولها إلى خلايا جذعية بشرية.
And then what they did in October
ومن ثم ما فعلوه في أكتوبر
is they took skin cells, turned them into stem cells
هو أنهم أخذوا خلايا جلدية وحولوها إلى خلايا جذعية
and began to turn them into liver cells.
وبدأوا في تحويلها إلى خلايا كبدية.
So in theory,
إذا نظريا،
you could grow any organ from any one of your cells.
يمكنك أن تكون أي عضو من أصل أي خلية من خلايا جسمك.
Here's a second experiment:
هاك تجربة ثانية:
If you could photocopy your body,
لو كان بإمكانك أن تصنع نسخة من جسدك،
maybe you also want to take your mind.
ربما تود أيضا أن تصنع واحدة لعقلك.
And one of the things you saw at TED
وواحدة من الأشياء التي رأيتموها على TED
about a year and a half ago
منذ حوالي عام ونصف العام
was this guy.
كان هذا الرجل. (إد بويدن)
And he gave a wonderful technical talk.
وأعطى حديثا تقنيا رائعا.
He's a professor at MIT.
هو بروفيسور في جامعة MIT.
But in essence what he said
ولكن خلاصة ما قاله هو
is you can take retroviruses,
أنه يمكنك أن تأخذ فيروسات قهقرية،
which get inside brain cells of mice.
والتي تستطيع دخول خلايا دماغ الفئران.
You can tag them with proteins
و يمكنك أن تضع عليهم علامة بالبروتين
that light up when you light them.
والتي تشع ضوءا حين تضيئها.
And you can map the exact pathways
ويمكنك أن تصنع خريطة دقيقة للمسارات العصبية
when a mouse sees, feels, touches,
حين يرى الفأر، أو يشعر أو يلمس
remembers, loves.
أو يتذكر أو يحب.
And then you can take a fiber optic cable
ومن ثم يمكنك أن تأخذ سلكا من الألياف البصرية
and light up some of the same things.
وتضئ بعض من هذه المناطق المتشابهة.
And by the way, as you do this,
وبالمناسبة وأنت تفعل ذلك،
you can image it in two colors,
من الممكن أن تظهر في لونين،
which means you can download this information
مما يعني أنه يمكنك أن تحمل هذه البيانات
as binary code directly into a computer.
على شكل ترميز ثنائي على أي كمبيوتر.
So what's the bottom line on that?
إذن ما هي الخلاصة من هذه؟
Well it's not completely inconceivable
حسنا، إنه ليس شيئا يستحيل تخيله
that someday you'll be able to download your own memories,
أنه في يوم من الأيام ستتمكن من تحميل ذكرياتك الخاصة،
maybe into a new body.
ربما في جسد جديد.
And maybe you can upload other people's memories as well.
وربما يمكنك وضع ذكريات أشخاص آخرين في عقلك أيضا.
And this might have just one or two
وساعتها ربما يواجهك مشكلة او اثنتين صغار
small ethical, political, moral implications.
من الناحية الأخلاقية والأدبية والسياسية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just a thought.
مجرد فكرة.
Here's the kind of questions
(إرهاصات الخلود؟) وهذه هي نوعية الأسئلة
that are becoming interesting questions
التي أصبحت مثار اهتمام
for philosophers, for governing people,
للفلاسفة، لأهل الحكم،
for economists, for scientists.
للاقتصاديين، للعلماء.
Because these technologies are moving really quickly.
لأن هذه التقنيات تتطور بشكل كبير جدا.
And as you think about it,
وفي حين تفكر في ذلك،
let me close with an example of the brain.
دعني أختم بمثال للدماغ.
The first place where you would expect
أول مكان تتوقع
to see enormous evolutionary pressure today,
أن تجد فيه كم جبارا من الضغط التطوري اليوم،
both because of the inputs,
بسبب كل من كمية المعلومات المدخلة،
which are becoming massive,
والتي أصبحت هائلة،
and because of the plasticity of the organ,
وبسبب قدرة هذا العضو على المطاوعة،
is the brain.
هو الدماغ.
Do we have any evidence that that is happening?
هل نملك أي دليل على أن هذا هو ما يحدث حقا؟
Well let's take a look at something like autism incidence per thousand.
حسنا، دعنا نلق نظرة على شئ مثل معدل حدوث التوحد لكل ألف
Here's what it looks like in 2000.
هكذا كان في عام 2000.
Here's what it looks like in 2002,
هكذا كان في عام 2002،
2006, 2008.
عام 2006 وعام 2008.
Here's the increase in less than a decade.
وهذه هي الزيادة في أقل من عقد.
And we still don't know why this is happening.
ونحن لازلنا لا نعرف لماذا يحدث هذه.
What we do know is, potentially,
ما نعرفه هو أن هناك احتمال،
the brain is reacting in
أن الدماغ يتعامل بشكل
a hyperactive, hyper-plastic way,
فائق التفاعلية، بطريقة فائقة المطاوعة،
and creating individuals that are like this.
وصانعا أفرادا مثل هؤلاء. (العقل التوحدي هو عقل... (فائق الإدراك) (فائق الذاكرة) (فائق التركيز))
And this is only one of the conditions that's out there.
وهذه واحدة فقط من الأمراض الموجودة.
You've also got people with who are extraordinarily smart,
هناك أيضا أشخاص أذكياء بشكل غير عادي،
people who can remember everything they've seen in their lives,
أشخاص يمكنهم أن يتذكروا كل شئ مر بحياتهم،
people who've got synesthesia,
هناك أشخاص يعانون منالحس التبادلي،
people who've got schizophrenia.
أشخاص يعانون من انفصام الشخصية.
You've got all kinds of stuff going on out there,
توجد كل هذه الحالات المرضية في العالم،
and we still don't understand
ونحن لازلنا لا نفهم
how and why this is happening.
كيف ولماذا يحدث هذا.
But one question you might want to ask is,
ولكن هناك سؤال واحد ربما تود أن تسأله وهو،
are we seeing a rapid evolution of the brain
هل نحن نشاهد تطورا سريعا للعقل
and of how we process data?
ولكيفية تعاملنا مع البيانات؟
Because when you think of how much data's coming into our brains,
لأنك حينما تفكر في كمية البيانات التي تستقبلها أدمغتنا،
we're trying to take in as much data in a day
نحن نحاول أن نستقبل كم من البيانات في يوم واحد
as people used to take in in a lifetime.
مساو لما كان يستقبله الناس في حياة كاملة في الماضي.
And as you're thinking about this,
وأنت تفكر في ذلك،
there's four theories as to why this might be going on,
هناك أربع نظريات قد تفسر لماذا قد يحدث هذا،
plus a whole series of others.
بالإضافة إلى سلسلة كاملة من الأحداث الأخرى.
I don't have a good answer.
أنا لا أملك إجابة جيدة لها.
There really needs to be more research on this.
نحتاج فعلا أن يكون هناك المزيد من الأبحاث للإجابة عليها.
One option is the fast food fetish.
النظرية الأولى هي ولع الوجبات السريعة.
There's beginning to be some evidence
لقد أصبح هناك بعض الأدلة
that obesity and diet
على أن السمنة والنظام الغذائي
have something to do
لها علاقة
with gene modifications,
بالتغيرات الجينية،
which may or may not have an impact
والتي قد أو قد لا يكون لها تأثير
on how the brain of an infant works.
على طريقة عمل الدماغ في الجنين.
A second option is the sexy geek option.
النظرية الثانية هي خيار الغيك المثير.
These conditions are highly rare.
هذه الحالات نادرة بشدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But what's beginning to happen
ولكن ما بدأ في الحدوث
is because these geeks are all getting together,
هو أنه بسبب أن هؤلاء المهوسون بدأوا يتجمعون معا،
because they are highly qualified for computer programming
لأن لديهم كفاءة عالية في البرمجة
and it is highly remunerated,
ويتلقون أجرا عاليا،
as well as other very detail-oriented tasks,
بالإضافة إلى بعض المهمات التي تحتاج إلى تدقيق شديد في التفاصيل،
that they are concentrating geographically
مما يجعلهم يتركزون جغرافيا
and finding like-minded mates.
ويجدون زملاء لهم نفس طريقة التفكير.
So this is the assortative mating hypothesis
وهذه هي فرضية التزاوج بحسب التصنيف
of these genes reinforcing one another
والجينات الناتجة عن هذا التزاوج تقوي بعضها بعضا
in these structures.
في هذه الهياكل.
The third, is this too much information?
الفرضية الثالثة، هل هناك الكثير جدا من المعلومات؟
We're trying to process so much stuff
نحن نحاول أن نفهم الكثير من الأشياء
that some people get synesthetic
لدرجة أن بعض الناس سيصبحوا اصطناعيين
and just have huge pipes that remember everything.
ويمتلكون أنابيب ضخمة تستطيع تذكر أي شئ.
Other people get hyper-sensitive to the amount of information.
أشخاص أخرون سيصبحون حساسين بشدة لكميات المعلومات.
Other people react with various psychological conditions
آخرون سيتفاعلون بمجموعة مختلفة من الحالات النفسية
or reactions to this information.
أو ردود الأفعال لهذه المعلومات.
Or maybe it's chemicals.
أو ربما (الفرضية الرابعة) هي الكيماويات.
But when you see an increase
ولكنك حين ترى زيادة
of that order of magnitude in a condition,
مطردة بهذا الحجم لحالة ما،
either you're not measuring it right
إما أنك لا تقيسها بشكل صحيح
or there's something going on very quickly,
أو أن شيئا ما يحدث بسرعة رهيبة،
and it may be evolution in real time.
وقد يكون هذا تطور جيني يحدث في الوقت الفعلي.
Here's the bottom line.
وهذه هي خلاصة الموضوع.
What I think we are doing
ما أظن أننا نفعله
is we're transitioning as a species.
أننا نتحول كصنف بشري.
And I didn't think this when Steve Gullans and I started writing together.
ولم أكن أفكر في هذه حين بدأنا في الكتابة أنا و ستيف جالانس.
I think we're transitioning into Homo evolutis
أظن أننا نتحول إلى (هومو إيفوليوتيس)
that, for better or worse,
ذلك، للأفضل والأسوء،
is not just a hominid that's conscious of his or her environment,
ليس فقط الإنسانيون هم من لديهم وعي بالبيئة المحيطة بهم،
it's a hominid that's beginning to directly and deliberately
إنه من صنف الإنسانيين الذي سيبدأ ليؤثر مباشرة وعمدا
control the evolution of its own species,
في التحكم في تطور صنفه هو ذاته،
of bacteria, of plants, of animals.
وفي البكتيريا والنباتات والحيوانات.
And I think that's such an order of magnitude change
وأنا أظن أنه مع هذا الحجم من التغيير المطرد
that your grandkids or your great-grandkids
أحفادك أو أولاد أحفادك
may be a species very different from you.
قد يكونون صنفا مختلفا تماما عنك.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)